<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An old way of ending new controversies in a sermon preached to the comptroller, and the rest of the gentlemen of the honourable society of the Inner-Temple, on Sunday the 8th of January 1681/2, and at their special desire printed / by Thomas Pittis ...</title>
            <author>Pittis, Thomas, 1636-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12993711</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12993711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 396:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An old way of ending new controversies in a sermon preached to the comptroller, and the rest of the gentlemen of the honourable society of the Inner-Temple, on Sunday the 8th of January 1681/2, and at their special desire printed / by Thomas Pittis ...</title>
                  <author>Pittis, Thomas, 1636-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Joanna Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Epistles of John, 1st, II, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96370:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN OLD WAY OF ENDING <hi>NEW CONTROVERSIES;</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED To the <hi>COMPTROLLER,</hi> and the reſt of the Gentlemen of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Society of the <hi>Inner-Temple:</hi> On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> 1681/2. and at their ſpecial Deſire Printed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS PITTIS,</hi> D. D. one of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quiſquis ab Eccleſiâ ſegregatus adulterae jungitur, à promiſſis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſeparatur.</hi> 
               <bibl>Cypr. <hi>De Unitat. Eccleſ, Cath.</hi> Pag. 181.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Iſidor. Peluſiot. Epiſt. Lib. 4. Epiſt. 67.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Joanna Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96370:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the <hi>Comptrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>INNER TEMPLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat I expoſe an accidental <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to the world, who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been ſo ſhie and wary; is only from the force of your command, delivered to me with that uſual ſtate (though complement too) which became men who at the time of preaching it had the Government of their houſe in their own hands. I owe much excuſe to the world but cannot reaſonably owe any to you, becauſe your Judgment upon it ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the Diſcourſe; and your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enjoyn'd me to deliver up the Copy. I was the more encouraged to do it, becauſe I heard you had made a Loyal Addreſs to the King; with
<pb facs="tcp:96370:3"/>
which, I hope the <hi>Sermon</hi> doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere. If you, or others may receive Advantage by the Peruſal, I care not whether it pleaſe the Multitude or no; (for Phyſick is not acceptable to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient) but ſhall reſt ſatisfied that I have obſerved your Commands: and that a Learned Body of Ingenious and Gentile Men are engag'd to defend it, whilſt I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>THO. PITTIS.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. <hi>13. 1682.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96370:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 2.24. former part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let that therefore abide in you which ye have heard from the beginning.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>AMongſt all thoſe various broods of Sects that ignorance and wilfulneſs have ſpawned in the World, there is none but is covetous that Antiquity ſhould Patronize it; never decrying its venerable Teſtimony, nor fearing its ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Anſwers, but when they diſtruſt its votes oppoſite to their preſent eſpouſals; Gray hairs being as well the Glory of an Opinion, as the Crown of the Old man. Hence is it that both Nations and Families have had ſuch ſevere Conteſts with each other, concerning the time of their firſt riſe, that from thence their Pedegree may appear Ancient, and they might gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown from the date of their Original.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96370:4"/>
And as in Perſons and Opinions, ſo in things too, <hi>quo antiquius eò melius,</hi> by how much the more Ancient a thing is, by ſo much the more is it prized and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by thoſe that covet a ſtrict inſpection into the Periods that did preceed their own, who meaſure the proportions of an infant World, and thus antedate their own Beings: How precious is a Script of <hi>Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſtus?</hi> Or the leaſt Workmanſhip of an inſpired <hi>Bezaleel?</hi> The ſmalleſt Leaf of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Herbal would be deemed a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Noble enough for the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch; How do we prize an old piece of <hi>Roman</hi> Coin? Or an antiquated <hi>Grecian</hi> Monument? Nor is this a Truth recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a general impreſs and confirmation, in reſpect of Artificial and Philoſophical Objects; but even Divinity too, having for its Author the Ancient of Days, values that which carries Age furrowed in its Face, and has Gravity and Years viſible on its Brow: And nothing ſeems more to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe and diſparage whatever wears the Title of Religion than to accuſe it of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and to bear the date of a late Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96370:4"/>
Hence <hi>Haman</hi> endeavoured from this Topick to brand the <hi>Jews,</hi> in that they uſed other Cuſtoms different from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Laws of the <hi>Perſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſther 3.</note> that their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty might render them odious to the King, being a crime it ſeems ſufficient to ruin them, when <hi>Mordecai</hi> could not bow to ſo inſulting a Favorite: St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he Preached the Goſpel at <hi>Athens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.</note> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice raiſed againſt the Truth of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by affirming him only to be a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forth of ſtrange Gods, and introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing new propoſitions into the World; <hi>Celſus</hi> when he profeſſedly wrote againſt the Truth and Divinity of the Chriſtian Inſtitutions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig.</hi> contra <hi>Celſum.</hi> Lib. 1.</note> thought he had caſt ſufficient blemiſh and contempt upon its Authority, when he had ſatisfied the World that it was new and unheard of:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Eccleſ. Hiſt. Lib. 1. Cap. 4.</note> And <hi>Euſebius</hi> aſſures us that it was a common ſtratagem, and uſual contrivance for the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from its firſt entrance, to be reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with its ſtrangeneſs and novelty; all mankind (as it ſeems) meaſuring the truth of things by their Antiquity, and general reception; and if we approach nearer to<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96370:5"/>
our own Confines we ſhall find the two great ſtruglers for the Weſtern Empire of Conſcience and Religion, ſtill endeavour to Crown their Opinions with old Age, and to gain both Strength and Honour to their Eſtabliſhment from time and dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The <hi>Romans</hi> would have the World to underſtand that the Pillars of their Church were founded with Chriſtianity, and that our Saviour himſelf once held thoſe Keys which he afterwards delivered to the Papal Succeſſion. But though they had a firm Foundation, they have built upon it a tottering Superſtructure. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant would willingly obliterate the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of a late Reformation, and will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedate <hi>Luther</hi> and the <hi>German</hi> heats, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the midſt of a bloody Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſome being willing to Travel to <hi>Bohemia</hi> to derive their Principles from <hi>John Hus,</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſending us to our own <hi>Wiccliffe,</hi> but eating through the Mountains to find out the more Ancient (though obſcure) <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes:</hi> others (and that more juſtly too) as if all this will not yet evince their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96370:5"/>
Aged, will Travel farther to the Churches Cradle, and find out the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in which our Saviour himſelf was laid, and from his Mouth receive their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, reviving what might ſeem dead, having for ſome time been buryed in the duſt and rubbiſh of mens Inventions; and freeing it from thoſe Burdens and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions which a gainful Intereſt, and bold Preſumption had loaded it withal, thus cauſe that to abide in them which Chriſtians heard from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Antiquity then being ſo powerful a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to perſuade to Religion, that all ſtrive to catch and graſp it; I ſhall eaſily prevail for a diligent attention ſince what I deliver ſhall be that which has been heard from the beginning.</p>
            <p>In which Text we have an Exhortation both Grave and Seaſonable; Grave it is, avoiding thoſe levities and varniſh which Novices uſe to wrap their late and uncouth Opinions in, that they may be ſnatched at with the more greedy Appetite: As Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians put their bitter Pills in ſweet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that the Patient may ſwallow them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96370:6"/>
with the greater delight: and ſeaſonable was this advice too; ſince <hi>Simon,</hi> and the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> did now attempt the murdering Chriſtianity when it was juſt born; as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> cruelty, drinking in, with an inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thirſt, the blood of Infants, would have Crucified our Saviour in his Cradle, before Age had given him Strength and Stature, not only to publiſh his Fathers Meſſage, but even to bear his own Croſs. Nay leaſt this accurſed, and Antichriſtian Sect, provoking their deſires to unlawful Luſts, detracting from Chriſtianity by an impious and incoherent intermixture of Jewiſh and Heathen Rites and Practices, with what was now Solemn in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and Sacred by its eſtabliſhment, ſhould not be able to impede, or retard, the moſt glorious flouriſh of Goſpel Truth, and forbid the ſpreading of the Chriſtian Church, that Noble Vine but newly Planted; <hi>Cerinthus</hi> alſo now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, with all the wild Boars of the Forreſt, if poſſibly, to undermine and root her up, denying the Divinity of its firſt Author: An Heretick ſo foul and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96370:6"/>
that the bleſſed Pen-man of my preſent Text would not come into the ſame Bath in which the wicked <hi>Cerinthus</hi> waſhed, leaſt he ſhould be defiled with that water which had touched ſo filthy and loathſome a Carcaſs; and the Bath it ſelf, ſenſible of its own pollution, ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fall to make a Grave for its ſelf and poſſeſſours.</p>
            <p>In the Exhortation then there are three Parts preſented to our view (1.) A Duty, <hi>Let that therefore abide in you,</hi> (2.) Its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Which ye have heard,</hi> (Laſtly) The Motive and Inducement to the Duty, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was <hi>from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt crave leave to invert the Parts, though it ſhall make no alteration in the Sence; that firſt the Object being explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Motive propoſed, the Duty may be with the greater facility preſſed and embraced. (1.) Then, Let the Object in the Text exhibite it ſelf; and this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what ye have already heard. As Faith it ſelf is generated by the Ear, ſo what you have heard is nothing elſe but the Object of your Faith; for thus does the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96370:7"/>
Apoſtle conclude the inference; <hi>Faith cometh by Hearing, and Hearing by the Word of God,</hi> (Rom. 10.17.) But as Hearing is the Conduit to convey Faith, ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is it the decoy to infidelity; becauſe there are many falſe Prophets gone forth into the World; and a ſeeming truth may make the ſame impreſſion with truth it ſelf. Nay, our bleſſed Saviour, that he might not leave us without due Caution, has informed all Ages and Generations, that there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets; yea! and ſhall ſuperadd Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to their Oratory, not only to amuſe the World, but to gain credit and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to their Doctrine; inſomuch that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall prevail to the diſmal ſhaking of the ſtrongeſt Oakes, and the rooting up the talleſt Cedars of <hi>Libanus;</hi> even to the putting a falacy upon the very Elect, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24.) The Ear of Man, being the recepticle of all Sounds, no wonder that it admits the ſounding Braſs and tinckling Cymbal, as well as the Trumpets of the Sanctuary. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> may be as as welcome to the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96370:7"/>
as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples at <hi>Antioch.</hi> If a vain-glorious <hi>Herod</hi> has but Confidence enough to make an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, though repugnant to the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, nor wonder that it makes ſuch an impreſs upon the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that they give ſhouts, with the lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Acclamations, and attribute to him the Wiſdom of a Deity, who is ſcarce en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the Prudence of a Man; (<hi>Acts</hi> 12.22.) If a mechanick Silverſmith, prompted with no other motive than what Avarice and Intereſt can dictate, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently plead for the Shrines of <hi>Diana;</hi> the clamorous Multitude ſhall ſoon cry out, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians, (Act.</hi> 19.28.) So eaſily captivated are vulgar Affections, and of ſo ſlender a value is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Applauſe. The mutable Croud will change their Religion with their Garments, and is of that ſtill which is of the neweſt faſhion. As if <hi>novitas eſſendi</hi> were the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Devotion, and Age were not the Meaſure of Divinity. As if the neweſt Stamp were to be deemed alwaies the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Metal; and the laſt dictate of a falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96370:8"/>
Underſtanding were the beſt object for the Wills embracement: Then indeed our Saviours Argument would be nothing but a Sophiſm againſt Phariſaical Devor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>From the beginning 'twas not ſo, (Matth.</hi> 19.8.) nor would the Advice in the Text be ſolid; <hi>Let that therefore abide in you which ye have heard from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not every thing that pleaſes the Ear that muſt be cloſeted and lodged in the Heart, leſt Tares being ſowed amongſt the Corn, they ſpread, and flouriſh, and o'er-ſhadow the Grain: Our Saviour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knowing our promptitude to imbibe what might ſeem pleaſant, and to ſwallow Poyſon if wrap'd up in gilded Pills; leaves a grave and ſevere Caveat, <hi>Take heed what ye hear, (Mark</hi> 4.24.) and leſt our ſtrict obſervation of the matter ſhould make us regardleſs of the manner of performance; St. <hi>Luke</hi> delivers it, <hi>Take heed how you hear; (Luke</hi> 8.18.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.</note>) As well knowing that too too few look to their Feet when they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Sanctuary of the Lord, but are more ready to offer the Sacrifice of Fools, then to hear their Vices redargued as they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96370:8"/>
ought; not allowing themſelves ſo much either of time, or ſeriouſneſs, as to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they do evil. Theſe are ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> reprehends,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de bono perſever. lib. 2. cap. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Audientes corporis ſenſu qui non audiunt cordis aſſenſu;</hi> who uſe the Word and Doctrine of the Goſpel only as an Ornament to deck the Head, not as a foundation to eſtabliſh the Heart; that hang it only as a Jewel in the Ear, but reſerve it not as a choice treaſure to enrich the Soul; whoſe practice is juſt oppoſite to St. <hi>James</hi>'s advice, they will not lay apart all filthineſs and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, that they may receive with meekneſs the engrafted Word which is able to ſave their Souls; (<hi>James</hi> 1.21.) Too too many ſooner bow their Ears to what may irritate and provoke their luſt; to the frothy diſcourſes of deceitful Tongues; to bold Rants, and jovial Catches; to thoſe lewd Sonnets that are the looſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures of looſer brains, which being heated with vice, boil over in ſcum and filth: men are more attentive to new Oaths, and unheard of Blaſphemies; to ſuch as jeſt, and droll down Religion, that it may no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96370:9"/>
longer interrupt the pleaſant wickedneſs of a degenerated Age; to ſuch as are ſo hardy as to Lampoon Heaven, and make Satyrs againſt the Quire above; that would, if either method might prevail, Flout, or Hector, God Almighty from his Throne; whoſe Language is more exalted than rayling <hi>Rabſhekeh</hi>'s. Theſe, that are ſpots in our Feaſts of Charity, become the only Perſons worthy of Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; their black Language is viewed, and gazed on, as the brighteſt Oracles; every ſhrug raiſes admiration, and a little ſmile is enough to authorize a great jeſt: as if theſe wandering Comets were of more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity than the fixed Stars; and the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Hell to be more diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended than the Voice of Heaven. God at once pardon and remedy it. The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the Moſt High may take up the Lamentation of him that firſt gave them their Commiſſion. <hi>To whom ſhall we ſpeak and give warning that they may hear? Behold their Ear is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and they cannot hearken; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the word of the Lord is to them a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96370:9"/>
reproach; they have no delight in it.</hi> (Jer. 6.10.)</p>
            <p>Some indeed are much for the Ear; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to thoſe ſcandals and reproaches that the envious man will caſt upon him whom his malice ruins, or his ambition undermines: others, even in Sacred things, reduce devotion all to the Ear; and when God, principally requires the Heart in Prayer, theſe will give little elſe but the Ear in Hearing; being as partial in their Sacrifices towards God, as they are in their Cenſures towards their Neighbours, as if the Decalogue were now aboliſhed, and the only Command were, <hi>Hear O Iſrael.</hi> 'Twas the error of the <hi>Euchites</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Praying, and 'tis as great an error to be always Hearing: as if the School of our Saviour ſhould not only be enjoyned Biennial ſilence, but be for ever mute. <hi>Porphyry</hi> indeed, (that great Blaſpemer, big with malice againſt the Heavens) when checks of Conſcience forced him to ſpeak out ſomething of the reſults of his own Reaſon, teacheth us to Sacrifice our Souls to God in ſilence with Chaſt thoughts;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96370:10"/>
How Chaſt men are at thoſe ſeaſons that ought to be attended with Solemnity, and Devotion, it would be preſumption in any to judg: but ſure I am that they put in practice this ſage advice of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Porphyry,</hi> who thus pretend to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in ſilence: As if he that made the Tongue as well as the Ear, did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the one to make Oblations of Prayer and Praiſe, as well as the other to Hear his Word; or he that Created the whole man would be contented with a partial Sacrifice. And now if any one has Ears to hear let him hear; and not only ſo, but retain alſo what he has heard; ſo will the Exhortation in my Text be embraced: <hi>Let that therefore abide in you which ye have heard from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus endeavoured to free man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from ſuch diſeaſes and diſtempers in Religion; I muſt now crave leave to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the recommendation of our duty; and perſuade men to the diligent atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that Sacred Word, which is able to make us wiſe unto Salvation, and be greedy to receive it, when not extended
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96370:10"/>
in an adulterated hand: For as we cannot hear without a Preacher, ſo he cannot Preach that is not ſent, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.) Some men are like thoſe large tongued women in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time,<note place="margin">Tert. de prae. Scrip. Hae. et. cap. 41.</note> who though a perſon of excellent Language, was yet forced to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt them that being ſo liberal of their Speech in Private, conjectured they had, if not Rhetorick, and Reaſon, yet yet words enough, to declame in Publick; whom the Father reprehends in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition:<note place="margin">Tert. de virg. velandis. cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Non permittitur mulieri in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiâ loqui, ſed nec docere, nec tinguere; nec offerre; nec ullius virilis muneris, nedum ſacerdotalis officii, ſortem tibi vindicare:</hi> or like thoſe that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> complains of, in the ſecond Chapter of his firſt Book of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> that are <hi>garruli ratiocinatores, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiores quam capaciores;</hi> that are pratling Diſputants, more ſhrill than rational: How many diſmal mourning ſouls, whoſe Education never advanced them to any degree above Mechaniſm, ſteal away the Prieſts Office, as <hi>Neanthus</hi> did <hi>Orpheus</hi>'s Harps, who thinking to effect the ſame wonders <hi>Orpheus</hi> did, and make Woods
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96370:11"/>
and Trees dance after his melody, played ſo ill, that the very Dogs, being affrighted at his ſtrange noiſe, tore him all in pieces. When we hear therefore, we muſt not throw away our attention upon uſurping Schiſmaticks; whoſe very Preaching is their Crime, becauſe without a Sacred and Divine Commiſſion; and ſince giving them Audience is their encouragment, it can no leſs involve ſuch eaſie Auditors in a ſnare and guilt.</p>
            <p>And yet, ſince the Text exhibits ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that always has been heard, it does not only imply our duty of attention, but preſents us with what we ought to hear; and thats the Goſpel; what both the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples were acquainted with from the beginning: And ſince, in that Sacred Teſtimony to our Saviour, there are various Truths which make up its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture; thoſe things are firſt to be heard and received that are in themſelves moſt Fundamental; <hi>Primarium dogma de Chriſti divinitate,</hi> (ſays <hi>Juſtinian</hi>) the chief Doctrine of the Divinity of our Saviour, without which the Foundation being ſunk, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96370:11"/>
whole fabrick muſt of neceſſity be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: For ſince his Divinity gives merit to his Paſſion, by which his temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment bears proportion to an infinite offence; detract from his Deity and you ſpot his ſufferings; and then if he be a Lamb with blemiſh, though he be ſlain, he cannot ſatisfie; and ſo the ſeries of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation becomes diſordered, and our eternal ſafety undermined.</p>
            <p>And now perhaps ſome wiſe perſon might take advantage to exhibite, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture at a Catalogue of Fundamentals; and a clamorous Adverſary might with as much confidence and triumph demand them; but when we receive a particular of Explicits, we may then attempt a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Fundamentals. In the mean time, ſince Faith is the general condition of the Goſpel; and, <hi>He that believeth, and and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaved</hi> (Mark. 16.16.) Methinks we need diſturb our ſelves no further for Fundamentals, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine what compleats that one thing, Faith. And though Intereſt and Opinion have rendered it as different from it ſelf as one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96370:12"/>
mans fancy from another, and we have created almoſt as many varieties of Faith, not only as there are Nations in the world, but men too; (multitudes dealing by it as <hi>Caligula</hi> did by the Image of <hi>Jupiter Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piacus</hi> when he took from it its head of Gold, and put upon it an head of Braſs;) yet if we will admit the Father of the Faithful: to explain the difficulty, we ſhall find that the practice of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>Abraham,</hi> (who is exhibited as a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for Goſpel believers;) will give us a proſpect of that Faith which had its being from the beginning. And though there are many acts of this ancient Faith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to our peruſal in New Teſtament Pages, yet there are two comprehenſive of all the reſt, to wit Belief and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For when he to whom all things are poſſible, had promiſed a branch ſhould ſprout forth from this dry Root; and that he would be his ſhield, and great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (<hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1.) <hi>Abraham</hi> did not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word of a Deity, who, he knew, was able to controul the world, and alter the power of ſecond Cauſes according to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96370:12"/>
the pleaſure of his own will: but ſtedfaſtly aſſented to the truth of what God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; relying on it with Faith and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. And as this Action includes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Promiſes, ſo the ſecond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes obedience to the Commands; and it was that work which St. <hi>James</hi> ſays juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, even the offering up his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon the Altar (<hi>Jam.</hi> 2.21.) So that to ſum up the whole Goſpel in one word, that you may here have preſented in an Epitome, what I humbly beg may abide in you: He that believes the Promiſes, ſo as to obey the Precepts; that accepts his Saviour as a King to rule, and a Prophet to teach, as well as a Prieſt to make at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement; and, conſequently, ſubmits to the authority of his Laws, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Miniſtry and Diſcipline; that relies upon the merits of his Croſs, and perſues the ſteps of his vertuous Life, in order to the ſecuring his eternal Safety: He is the Perſon who retains what he has already heard; and he need not fear any deceiptfull Impoſition, ſince he embraces that which was from the beginning. Which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96370:13"/>
minds me of the Motive here propoſed, to fortifie our reſolutions, that what we have heard may abide in us, ſince it is no more than what was delivered from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>In Philoſophical Propoſitions we uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deem thoſe moſt certain that later expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments prove, and evince: but, in Divine Truths, thoſe are beſt that were from the beginning. Time, which is in a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed flux, being in this like the ſwifteſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, that carry down to us what is light and frothy; but ſink that which is grave and ponderous: and indeed Reaſon, which is the reſult of our nobler part, if not diſturbed by paſſion or intereſt, is the ſureſt guide in the midſt of perplexities; and this does, upon the firſt proſpect of Religion, lead us to that which was from the beginning. And Chriſtianity being that which pretends to be firſt begotten in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, though brought forth here on Earth, owning not leſs than a God for its Author, whoſe great propoſitions are made up of Eternal Truths; and ſince the Apoſtles were inſpired to a compleat delivery of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96370:13"/>
what was at firſt Preached by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the ſame Doctrine, by a continued ſucceſſion, having been derived and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to Poſterity; it follows, by an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable concluſion, that the ſureſt way, for us, to whom theſe Principles are exhibited, when any Objection, or different Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preſents it ſelf, to ſtartle our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions; is to perſue the firſt Rule, and follow that which was delivered from the beginning.</p>
            <p>But ſince the various ſubdiviſions of thoſe that intitle themſelves to the names of Chriſtians, pretend to thoſe infallible Maxims treaſured up in the Sacred Book; there muſt be left a Judg of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; or elſe there will remain no way of freedom from preſent diſturbances, or certain method of reducing thoſe who, being too fond of their own fancies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely adhere to their private Opinions, to the detriment of Chriſtianity, and ruin of themſelves, and the obſtruction of Peace and Unity in the world. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, although certain in it ſelf, being conveyed to us in Words
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96370:14"/>
and Language which may admit of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Conſtructions, ſuitable either to the uſe of words, or the apprehenſions of men, cannot, (without ſuch a judgment upon it as may oblige the various extravagancies of mankind to ſilence, and a paſſive ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, whatever may be their internal belief;) be ſufficient Clue to lead us out of theſe Labyrinths: Though had the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of its Followers juſtly meaſured and proportioned Underſtandings, rightly to diſcern the Fruits wrapped in thoſe Leaves, it muſt appear to every man, the beſt, and only Conductor in the world. But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every perſon uſurps Authority to interpret, and every Illiterate and Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical head, if he has not reaſon to confirm his Gloſs, has confidence however to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an Inſpiration; neceſſity inforces us to ſeek ſome method to quiet our minds, and to allay the briskneſs of our own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and thoſe heats and fury, that our warmer contrivances introduce into the world: that ſo we may arrive at ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty as is poſſible to be obtained, of what was heard from the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96370:14"/>And though I ſhall not attempt the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any to St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, nor beg that <hi>Rome</hi> may be the place of Umpire; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no need of fetching water from <hi>Tiber</hi> when we have clear Fountains at our own doors; yet reaſon muſt force this confeſſion, that ſince it is not the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the ſence, of Scripture that is the proper Guide of life; there muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſome Interpretation, ſince our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to one another may be the ſame with the Eunuch to St. <hi>Philip,</hi> how ſhall we Read without ſome Interpreter? And then the laſt queſtion will be who are thoſe that are moſt likely to exhibit to us the exact deſign of Scripture Phraſe, and the infallible Rule that leads to Life?</p>
            <p>To produce therefore ſome concluſions touching this controverted, and difficult, Queſtion; Thoſe muſt certainly beſt inform one of the meaning of a Sermon, that have had the moſt familiar acquaintance with the Preacher; Capacities alſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and Fidelity to deliver what they have received from the mouth of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: upon which propoſition thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96370:15"/>
that ſeem moſt rational, attempt the proof of the Apoſtles Writings that are but the firſt Commentaries upon that Goſpel which our Saviour Preached and Uſhered into the World. From hence (ſecondly) it follows that the perſons who were the immediate Diſciples to thoſe Holy Penmen of Sacred Writ, having the advantages of Converſe, and the benefit of Audience, muſt of neceſſity be the fitteſt Judges of what is Controverted in matter of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which we pretend to derive from their Books and Writings: and there ſeems to remain nothing to be doubted, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Capacities to receive, or their Faithfulneſs to deliver, what they heard from the beginning. Their Capacities and Parts their Writings publiſh; their Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Honeſty their Lives declared; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had they either reaſon, or advantage thus to cheat, or impoſe upon, the world. And therefore thoſe Writers, who lived in the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, are firſt to be believed; that in difficulties and ſtraits we are to have recourſe unto; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the later to be leſs confided in,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96370:15"/>
as having met with greater and more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile oppoſition, and therefore ſubject to more intermixtures of heat and paſſion; and like Rivers, the further off the Fountain, the leſs do they retain of their firſt purity, and the greater mingling of different wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. As the nearer we are to the Fountain therefore, the clearer will the Stream be; ſo the nearer we Travel to that which was heard from the beginning, the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and infallible will our Guide and Rule be. But becauſe the reports and ſayings of Fathers are like melted Wax that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Image ſuitable to the Seal which makes the impreſſion; and perſons of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Churches, and Perſuaſions, deal with their Sentences, as young Sophiſters with a Text of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> by a diſtinction, or a figure, force them to countenance the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sentiments of their diſturbed minds: If we reſt here, we ſhall ſtill be as far from the end of Controverſie, as the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie from the beginning of Truth. To proceed further then, by the aſſiſtance of thoſe means our Reaſon dictates, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with prayers and humility of mind, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96370:16"/>
the inveſtigation of what we are to reſt in, as that which was from the beginning. A General Council would quickly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, did not an Empire now Canto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized; the oppoſite Intereſt of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among themſelves; diverſity of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſprung up among their Subjects; the great Prejudices that are in the world; and above all, over grown Popery, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſtruct its Juſtice and Freedom; and I might ſay, its Poſſibility too. As every Epiſcopal Church, therefore, was Planted, at the firſt, Independent of another; yet, to preſerve a Church Catholic upon Earth, admitting an Univerſal Union, Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Advice; and, by conſent, an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon particulars, by Authority from the whole. Every particular Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Church had a power of Diſcipline as well as Doctrine, committed to her truſt and managery; the firſt Planters convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downward, through a Sacred and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interupted Succeſſion, their Authority and Juriſdiction to this Age, and this Church, to which we now pretend a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In Controverſie and difference (as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96370:16"/>
the Caſe now ſtands with us) there can be no Example, or Rule, or more Rational Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, or Guide of Action, than that of the Primitive Planters of the Goſpel; which is, that the Inferior be regulated by the Advice and Authority of the Superior, and all ſubmit to the reaſonable reſolution of a National Council. Thus when the great diſpute about Circumciſion was raiſed at <hi>Antioch,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Syria,</hi> they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to which <hi>Antioch</hi> was ſubjected, being a place of Superior Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and the determination of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Judea,</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Repreſentatives of <hi>Antioch,</hi> fully ſilenced any farther Diſpute, and was the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſentence in which they acquieſced. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>But now, let not any men wonder that I call the Sentences of ſuch Councils In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible; ſince 'tis only uſing a Popiſh word, to expreſs Proteſtant ſence, to our ſelves, which overthrows the <hi>Roman</hi> claims over us. For this being applied to our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils here; our Church neither erring in Fundamentals, nor pretending to uſurp
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96370:17"/>
upon the Natural Priviledg of mankind to judge for themſelves as far as they are capable; but only aſſiſts and helps their Underſtanding in what they are deficient for want of Education; creating no New Articles of Faith: nay impoſing nothing on the belief of any, but what the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures have Authorized before; and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining nothing by its own power, but a limitation of the outward actions of men: its decrees in things that are thus the ſubject of human Laws, are either to be actually obeyed, or not publickly or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuoſly contradicted. And this is what I intend to be the ſence of the Infallible Sentence of a National Council, without which, Controverſie can never be ended, no Legiſlative Authority maintained, nor Peace and Order remain among us. For want of this moderate and ſober apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of things, men make themſelves lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe Penalties of Laws which good natured Magiſtrates ſo unwillingly inflict, and well meaning Chriſtians pity, and at the ſame time admire the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thoſe who are ſo hardy, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96370:17"/>
willing to deſerve them; eſpecially when they conſider, alſo, that the ſame perſons can be tamely ſilent, in Forain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where Principles of Religion more ſeverely contradict the Sentiments of their minds.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, indeed, a Council may err, unleſs they could put off their manhood, or to every decree have a freſh Inſpiration, or receive a Divine Teſtimony from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and yet it is to us Infallible; <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to ſilence our open Diſputes againſt it, and to be the Rule for our External Obedience. For frail men cannot poſſibly proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſearching out Divine Truths, than in the means, and way to find out the Revelation; and to underſtand it when it is found; leaving other indifferent things to the determination of thoſe who have Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over us: and thoſe means that I have mentioned ſeeming to be all that Reaſon and Diſcourſe, when not diſturb'd by Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy or Enthuſiaſm, are able to propoſe; and ſince the only Evidence we have to prove the objects of ſenſe againſt the bold denial of a confident <hi>Sceptick,</hi> is to call
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96370:18"/>
in many, againſt the obſtinacy of one, to give Teſtimony to what we ſee, or hear; and ſo to decide the difference betwixt us: If I err with ſubmiſſion to that Authority which I find the ultimate mean to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, my Crime, certainly, will not be ſo great, but a pardon will as neceſſarily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it; ſince the moſt gracious God does not require my action to be beyond the Sphere of my capacity; nor my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions to exceed the Powers of my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But the Authority of Councils, as hitherto ſtated, may ſeem too naked to be ſubmitted to; and yet we obſerved in the firſt times, a ready obedience to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, when backed by no Secular Power: It therefore they were obliging then, they engage us by another addition, and are ſtrengthened by a Civil Sanction. For as, when the Emperors became Chriſtians; what was before Eſtabliſhed by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his Apoſtles, and aſſerted by Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Biſhops, and Divines Congregated for that purpoſe, and drawn into Sacred Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, or Rules, received a Sanction from the Legiſlative Power reſident on Earth;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96370:18"/>
and were ſo embodyed with Imperial Laws, that the Magiſtrate was <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Tabulae:</hi> ſo the Proteſtant Church, among our ſelves, has its Foundations, in the Word of God, (derived downward from prime Antiquity) ſo inlaid with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Laws of our own Kingdom, that the one cannot be invaded with Triumph, but the other nods; nay totters, till it falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to inevitable ruine; and we need not a new Experiment to ſhew it. This every one, at length, believes, that is not, by being engaged in paſt miſchiefs, an enemy to both, and like <hi>Cataline,</hi> reſolved on fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture evils to juſtifie, or ſecure, thoſe that are paſt. But they, more diſtinctly, are acquainted with this, who are Learned in he Laws, than we, who being Divines, are willingly ſuppoſed ignorant of them. Yet this ſeems to be the great Reaſon why ſuch as deſign to invade the Crown, make a paſs at the Miter firſt, becauſe the Church is a Guard to the Palace, as well as the Palace a defence to the Church. Till this therefore be wounded, or removed, the diſturbers of the Peace
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96370:19"/>
of both, cannot, in probability, aſcend the Throne, nor place a Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> there.</p>
            <p>But, to return from this digreſſion; a National Council ought more eſpecially to determine the Controverſies among us, ſo as to oblige us to Peace, becauſe their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees are our own Acts, having choſen the perſons who repreſent us in it. Yet to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence doubts, and ſcruples, about this matter: whatever regard we may all have to tender Conſciences, that are not raw; the different thoughts of Worſhip among us, being ſuch as produce ſquabble and contentions, theſe, for our neceſſary eaſe and pleaſure, dividing us into ſeparated Clans; and theſe making us fit for Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, which, without any more Devils than our ſelves, may advance it ſelf into an actual Rebellion: And when vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſevere Conteſts about Religion have openly diſtinguiſhed men from each other, till they are hardly able to know themſelves; when private Diſpenſations, ſhall, in ſome caſes, vacat Publick Oaths by ſingle Interpretations, and in Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96370:19"/>
and Mental Reſervations men are able to out-ſtrip the Jeſuit himſelf; this is a way to remove the Pope, only by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him into our own Bellies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Union of Proteſtants among our ſelves, is the direct way to introduce Popery in Maſquerade (that I may uſe ſome Rhetorical words) and to imbrace what we declame againſt, and every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant is bound in his own capacity, to withſtand. But when Trade and Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions determine our Option, and paſt Acts (though evil in themſelves) muſt regulate our preſent, and future, deportment: when perſons chuſe their Articles of Creed, as well as various ways of Worſhip, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what they gain from thoſe with whom they ſeem Religiouſly to aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate: Conſcience and Chriſtianity do no longer guide them, but they give away their choice to Clients, Trade, and (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Divines) to the preferments of this World; and, all this while, 'tis Earth becomes their Supreme God, and Secular Intereſt governs their Religion. When Affairs therefore, through our own indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96370:20"/>
or the wickedneſs of others, are brought to this paſs, that men will vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their Oaths to preſerve Religion, or neglect Prayers to ſerve God; or attend Prayers to ſerve the Devil, and when, by ſuch methods as theſe, the Prologue is made to the diſmal Tragedy of a general Confuſion, 'tis time to call for a ſolemn Conſultation and for a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to interpoſe by Law, leaſt the Diſorders in what we call by the Ancient and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable name of Religion, may have too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere an influence on the State, and both be ruined by the ſame hands; ſince theſe are like <hi>Hypocrates</hi> Twins, that weep and laugh both together. 'Tis time therefore (at ſuch a Seaſon) to call upon our ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Laws to awake, whoſe Penalties have an equal Sanction with themſelves: and more eſpecially, becauſe puniſhment of Extravagant Offendors can be no Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, when the Chriſtian Religion is not concerned, but the various Intereſts of this World; and Penalties (in this Caſe) will only reſtrain the inordinate Affection of ſome men to their private
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96370:20"/>
Concerns in relation to their abode here; and teach them how to be Crucified to this World, that they may more eaſily aſcend into Glory in the next. 'Twill keep them ſteady whilſt they walk upon the Earth, when the Wings of their Ambition are clyp'd and pois'd; and cauſe them to grow better, by Religion, and Loyalty; that by a peaceable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of this Life they may enter into the Joy of our Lord. This (though, to ſome, it may ſeem ſevere) can be no violence offered to Conſcience, where we plainly ſee there is none at all. 'Twill be at moſt, no more than a limitation of Trade and Covetouſneſs, by reſtraining the Contentions and Ambition of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And now, if upon all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, a carping <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or angry <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt,</hi> ſhould blunder upon this Objection; that if the Church be infallible, <hi>quoad nos;</hi> ſo it was at the time of our withdrawing from the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we then breaking the Principal Bond of Truth and Union, muſt remain guilty of the greateſt Shiſm, unleſs we return to that<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96370:21"/>
Church from whence we have departed. It is, without any difficulty, replied, that he ſuppoſes that granted which we will not yield; for we were never lawfully ſubject to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, in reſpect of Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, any more than we were to the late Monſter of Traytors, in reſpect of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals: a proſperous Uſurpation giving them no better Title over our Church, which was diſtinct at its firſt reception of Chriſtianity, than the others poſſeſſion gave him right to his Sovereigns Throne; both being effected, by Subtilty, Force, and Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>Thus having, through this Diſcourſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited a great Character of Truth, which is prime Antiquity; and given ſome ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der account of what has been heard from the beginning: All that remains is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Apoſtles Exhortation to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and beg that ancient Truths may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in you. We have now had the Tryal of all things, let us therefore hold faſt that which is good: we have been too long toſſed in a ſtorm, but having at laſt, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at a ſafe Harbour, let us no more ſail
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96370:21"/>
out among the Rocks, nor put to Sea whilſt the Winds rage, and the Waves roar. The True, Ancient, and Apoſtolick Faith was, for ſome time, like the loſt ſheep; it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred about in a Wilderneſs of Error, and the by Paths of Hereſie and Schiſm, being torn and ſcratched with Briars and Thorns, not only till it was ſmeered with blood, but at laſt it became Naked Truth: Naked, indeed; for being void of Hypocriſie, it became Naked of Friends too: But now, ſince we have found the loſt ſheep no wonder that I Exhort you, as he did his Friends in the Goſpel; <hi>Rejoyce with me for I have found the ſheep that was loſt.</hi> And ſince the ſearch has been no leſs tedious, than in theſe times, full of hazard; let us no longer ſhift the Principles of our Religion, nor permit the wry Face of a man to draw our Souls and Bodies aſſide; but let thoſe Truths abide in us which we have heard from the begining. Why ſhould I uſe any Rhetorick to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade, when there is the Authority of God to command? <hi>Tacitus</hi> informs us of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Soldiers; <hi>Imperium potius quam concilium ſequebantur;</hi> A word of Command was
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96370:22"/>
more to them than perſuaſion or advice in a formal Speech. And ſhall we that march under our Saviours Banner be more diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient than a Heathen Militia? Why ſhould we not for Edification ſubmit to true Decency and Order, that we may no longer be like <hi>Samaritans</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe kinder Correſpondences with each other? As the Apoſtle therefore Exhorts thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> who, though diſperſed, were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſtian Faith and Diſcipline: ſo let me, with all Charity and Affection beg, that you would hold faſt your Profeſſion (<hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14.) Can we reaſonably part with the Glorious Goſpel which promiſes Crowns and everlaſting Rewards; that takes care of us after we are Dead, and leaves us neither in Purgatory or the Grave; nay, that free us from the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell, and advances us to the Joys of Heaven: We cannot once depart from our Religion, but at the ſame time we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon our ſelves, exchange our Reaſon for Folly and Madneſs, and barter our precious Souls for trifles; and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in this exchange? <hi>What is a man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96370:22"/>
profited</hi> (ſays our Saviour) nay, how is a man utterly undon if, <hi>to gain the whole world, he loſes his own ſoul?</hi> (Matth. 16.26.) Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what you are capable of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, and when you have found a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be ſound, take St. <hi>Pauls</hi> advice to <hi>Timothy; Hold faſt the form of ſound words,</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.) Many of our fierce and ſtaring Seperatiſts, like their Anceſtors of another denomination (the <hi>Papiſts</hi> I mean) embrace Principles and Ways of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, though they underſtand them not. As <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Toſcan</hi> Rights and the Soothſayings of the <hi>Salian</hi> Prieſts, <hi>Vix Sacerdotibus ſuis intellecta, ſed quae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari vetat Religio.</hi> Scarce apprehended by their Prieſts themſelves, but yet their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Religion forbid a change. But that Goſpel which has been heard from the beginning, is no Airy Doctrine to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed into a Cloud; nor ſo hot, as to be raiſed into a Pillar of Fire: we are not to be conducted as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were of old; nor, thanks be to God, and a Chriſtian Government, is the Church yet in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs condition; our Principles are as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96370:23"/>
Plain as Honeſt; and our Religion as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, as it is Rational; and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, if our Practice Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponds, which the Church of <hi>England</hi> pretends a reverence for; by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, being ſubmitted to with meekneſs, will be ſufficient to ſave our Souls, through him who firſt publiſhed it to the World, and died to make ſatisfaction for our ſins. Let this therefore abide in you; that you may not be, like Waves of the Sea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rolling, and driven which way a Storm pleaſes; but ſetled, and immova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, always abounding in the Work of the Lord; which let God Cooperate and ſtrengthen you in, for Chriſt Jeſus's ſake; <hi>To whom with the Father and his Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be all Glory, and Honour, now, and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
